Hello, welcome everyone. It is May 20th,
2025. We're in active math stream number
13.1 with Alexi Tumi discussing disco by
monoidal categories for active
inference. This should be a very
exciting and useful presentation and
stream. So, thank you very much for
joining and looking forward to learning
more.
Yeah, thanks a lot. Um, so thanks a lot
for the invite. Um, yeah, I guess um, as
I was saying just a couple of minutes
ago, um, I'm very much looking forward
to this talk and it's a bit of a
challenge for me, I guess, in a sense
that I'm no expert in active inference.
So, I'll I'll do my best at explaining
what I think active inference is about.
And uh I also try to uh yeah convince
the audience here that um disco uh this
Python library uh for uh string diagrams
is um promising way to to experiment
with active inference. So I guess um
most of the the references I I'll be
using for for today would be this uh
main disco pi paper. Um, you can also
check out the the documentation on on
GitHub. It's quite extensive. We've got
plenty of examples and notebooks to play
around with. Um, and then I'll give a a
small glimpse of what the disco software
is used for. So, this idea of QNLP,
quantum natural language processing,
which is what motivated the the library
in the first place, what I wrote my PhD
thesis about. um and um I guess I'll
give some introduction to category
theory uh which is the sort of
mathematical foundations on which uh
this copy is built and then I'll be
using mostly this um recent uh paper
from uh to Kleiner and SM on active
inference in string diagrams uh where
essentially they um use the same
mathematics that I was using for quantum
NLP and uh apply that to uh to active
inference and in a sense uh that's where
I learned all I know about active
inference. So I'll be giving a a summary
of the sort of theoretical background.
Um and then I'll be mostly showing some
screenshots from that paper to try and
show how that theory applies to active
inference in particular and then then we
can discuss u how disco could could be
used um to implement active inference
experiments. So yeah let's uh let's get
going. Um so I guess the main um
theoretical concept in disco is a box.
So, like we we we draw these boxes a
lot. And I guess uh I um I don't roast
coffee every morning, but I I grind
coffee. I make I brew coffee every
morning. And I I guess that's a
something that you're going to
understand in terms of a black box where
you you you put a bunch of uh inputs
like green coffee, beans, electricity,
roast level, start signal. Uh it could
be physical, it could be information.
These boxes are sort of abstract um
conceptual operations that just have uh
a name, a designated list of inputs and
outputs uh and a designated list of um
so yeah a designated list of inputs and
a designated list of outputs. So you've
got two sets uh the objects so the
things are on the wires uh and um boxes
um um have have names too and then you
have these two maps from boxes to lists
of wires. Um so that gives you all the
processes that you can talk about in
your in your theory. Um and then you can
translate one theory into another using
these morphisms of signatures. So uh
first if you have a box from X to Y, you
draw it with an arrow in this way. Um
and then if you have a morphism of
signature, what it means is you can
translate wires of one into lists of
wires in the second. Um and then you can
translate a box in one into a box in the
appropriate thing in the other. So if
you have um so this should be sigma
prime. I guess it's a typo but you
translate boxes in a way that respects
their inputs and outputs. Um and so
that's very useful because if you have
different uh kinds of of processes and
you want to translate between them um
that concept of morphism of signature is
going to be the the key one. Um and so I
guess um with that you can define um the
set of diagrams. So that's going to be
the main um the main uh definition for
this thought. Um and you start with a
signature and then you define diagrams
by induction. Uh where every box is a
diagram. Uh the identity is a diagram
and you draw it with just a bunch of
parallel wires. Um the composition of a
diagram from X to Y and Y to Z is also a
diagram. So you can if you have two uh
diagrams, you can plug them one after
the other. And then uh the tensor of two
diagrams is also a diagram. So if you
have f and frime, you can put them side
by side and you get something that goes
from xxx prime to y prime and that's it.
So you can um put um diagrams in
sequence and in parallel and you can
also do nothing. So this identity uh
diagram um and then I guess the subtlety
that we'll use here is that um well I
guess first you need to put some aums on
these. Uh so I guess you want tensor and
composition to be associative. Um you
want them to be unit. So if you compose
with the identity, it doesn't do
anything. If you tensor with the empty
diagram, so the identity on nothing on
the empty list, um that's also doing
nothing. And then you want just these
two equations that tell you that you can
uh switch identity and tensor. So ID of
tensor or tensor of ID is ID of tensor.
Um, and similarly for the composition,
the tensor of two compositions is going
to be the composition of the tensors.
And we'll see what that looks like in
terms of diagrams in a second. But as I
was saying, there's this sort of uh
nicity that you get is that if you take
a signature uh and you look at all the
diagrams uh that you generate from it,
that makes a new signature and you can
use that as a signature where
essentially now the boxes have diagrams
inside them. And so that's a way of
formalizing an idea of hierarchical
diagrams where essentially a sub diagram
will contain or a sub diagram is a box
that contains a diagram inside it. Um so
we'll use a lot of these hierarchical
diagrams where we'll see the the boxes
serve u to encode normalization. Um, and
so yeah, to get back to this main
equation, I guess that's the only
equation you need to remember. And you
don't actually need to remember it
because essentially you got it built
into your visual system. So that's the
sort of um main argument for why you
should um you should use string diagrams
is that essentially they encode this
very natural way of looking at processes
as uh things on the plane where the
axioms become um the axioms become um
just manipulation of these uh of these
diagrams geometrically. So for example
this um this axiom of naturality where
um you exchange the composition and the
tensor this amounts to having either uh
the boxes composed uh first sequentially
and then in sequence or first in
sequence and then sequentially and that
gives you the same um the same diagrams
in the end. So well the only thing that
counts is how things are connected I
guess is the the main idea for that
axum. And so you can apply that to
cooking. Um the ingredients are going to
be your wires. Um the steps the cooking
steps are going to be your boxes. And
now anything that you can compose with
these cooking steps will be a recipe. It
takes a bunch of uh inputs like eggs and
gives you a bunch of outputs like whites
and yolks, right? And yeah, I guess um
this this aum of exchanging tensor and
composition essentially it amounts to
formalizing what we mean by
independence. So if we have two boxes
that are not connected like cracking uh
here and cracking here, we can perform
them in any order. Uh if independent, it
doesn't matter how we decompose this
tensor of composition.
Um so yeah I guess
um let's look at what this diagram looks
like in Python. Um so that's the main
feature of disco is you get this very
nice syntax for expressing any such
string diagram as uh essentially as a
Python function. So you you start by
declaring some types for the ingredients
of your recipe like egg, white and yolk.
You have a box for cracking an egg and
giving whites and yolk. You have these
parameterized boxes. So merge, you can
merge anything. So any X and that takes
two X's and gives you an X. And now to
define the diagram on the right, you'll
just define a Python function. Declare
its inputs and its outputs. And now if
you take X and Y for the two eggs, you
crack them, you get AB is a white yolk
pair, CD is a white yolk pair. So you
can merge the whites together, merge the
yolks together and return. So you get
your diagram and you can draw it. So
this output on the right is actually
what disco gives you as a as a drawing.
And you can also write it in terms of
purely uh pure operations of tensor and
composition. So this uh add symbol is
how you do the the tensor the parallel
composition and this these chevrons do
the sequential composition. And here you
notice that we need this special box for
the swap, right? Like uh at first with
just tensor and composition, you can
only do planer uh processes. So here you
need this special swap box that takes
yoke and white and gives you white and
yoke. Um so yeah, I guess that's the
sort of simplest example of how to use
this copy is you can define a bunch of
types. um define a composite model uh
composite um diagram out of these uh
basic uh steps, basic boxes and and
types and then you can draw the result.
I guess drawing the result would be the
first step. Uh and in a second we'll
look at um what else you can do with
diagrams. So a more interesting example
I guess in our context will be um a
generative model as a diagram. So on on
the left you have the sort of basic
example of a probabilistic model where
you have random variables numbered x1 to
to x5. Um and then you have these
arrows. Um I guess um here some arrows
are designated as sort of input arrows.
Um here on on the left uh x2 and x3 are
sort of variables that I guess you get
to control or you you can choose some um
some distributions over these. Um then
you have some hidden variables like this
x1, x2 and x4 and you have um observed
variables right the x5 and x3 would be
the things that you can actually observe
in the end. And then sort of implicitly
in every such um probabilistic model
graphical model you would have a
conditional probability distribution for
every variable given the variables that
point to it. Right? And so in the world
of string diagrams, these conditional
probability distributions become the the
important thing in a sense like the I
guess here the labels you could almost
forget about these labels X1 to X5. They
help to make the correspondence here.
But the actual important operations are
these conditional distributions. So X1
well you need a distribution on it. It's
this uh latent variable. So that's going
to be your A. It's going to be a prior
on on X1. And then you you need a
distribution for B that gives you X4
based on X1 X2. You need a distribution
C that takes uh gives X5 given X4, X2,
X3 and so on. And then here you also
need this important operation that does
copying, right? So here the variable X2
will be used um in the in the
conditional distribution for X4 and for
X5. So you'll feed it to B and you'll
feed it to C. So you need to copy it,
right? You need to broadcast this um uh
whatever input you feed in here, right?
Um and so if you take um a distribution
that's uh non-trivial, well, this will
create some in this will create some u
correlation between those distributions,
right? Um and so at the end, what you
get are the observed variables which are
these outputs of your of your diagram.
And so you get this mechanical
translation where every um every
probabilistic model can be faithfully
encoded as such a string diagram. Um the
the wires are the random variables. Um I
guess the subtlety here is like the
wires
um up to this copying right. So here the
variable x2 appears uh twice. So you
need to split the wire in some some
formal sense. Um the boxes are
conditional probability distributions
that define your model. Um and the
diagrams are the generative models
themselves.
Right? So here's what the same code
would look like in Disco Pi. Again,
you're going to instantiate a bunch of
types for X1 to X5. And then you're
going to have these boxes ABC. And you
can define your model as a Python
function that takes a bunch of variables
and just does the usual thing. And I
guess the magic of of these Python
decorators is that your function here is
not going to be interpreted as an actual
function. It's going to be executed sort
of symbolically. And these variables X2
and X3 are going to be turned into the
input wire of your diagram. And then
these x5 x x3 will be the output wires
of your diagram. And so in a sense what
disco pi gives you is a sort of domain
specific language where you can write
any such uh generative model and you
will get a data structure for it. So I
guess today I won't have much time to
get into the the data structure
underlying these but I I guess there's
sort of uh two main ones two main ways
of understanding these diagrams is the
first one is as a sort of sequence of
layers where each uh layer of your
diagram is like for example this first
layer you've got a box A in parallel
with copying in parallel with another
copying the second layer would be B in
parallel with a bunch of identities and
the last layer code BC. So this sort of
list-like representation is very
convenient for drawing. And I guess if
we go back to our cooking example, this
is why you get to see these sort of
stacking of boxes is essentially it's
more convenient to have one box at each
layer. So you just get a list of these
guys, a list of operations that you
perform. Um and then there's sort of the
graph-like representation which is the
more natural one when you think of a
graphical model. They're called
graphical because it's a graph, right?
So I guess discoy gives you this ability
of going back and forth between graph
like and sort of list like and the
listike operation is also how you define
um the evaluation of these diagrams. So
we'll get to see that in in a minute.
These diagrams you can draw them you can
store them as combinatorial
representations of of graphs. Um and I
guess the main point is you can evaluate
them and you can do experiments with
them.
So let's get to that. The I guess the
the theory we need behind this is u is
that of strict monoidal categories. So
I'll just say category for short um
because I guess they'll all be strict
and monoid uh in this talk. And
essentially um once you know what a
signature is. So this set of um of of
wires and boxes with domain co- domain
you can define a category as a signature
with a way of evaluating diagrams
essentially. So a way of taking a
composition of boxes and wires to give a
single box. So first you need a way of
interpreting identity uh for each
object. you need a way of of
interpreting uh composition and you need
a way sequential and parallel
composition right so now essentially a
category will be a concrete way of
interpreting these diagrams um and I
guess um the the key sort of structural
theorem for well okay let's first look
at some uh some examples um so I guess
the main example we've seen so far of a
category is the category of wires and
diagrams where the objects are these
these wires the lists of inputs or
outputs and the diagrams are this
composition of boxes that you can
represent combinatorally um as graphs.
Um and then
um
the I guess the most natural
interpretation of these um if you come
from some sort of mathematical
background would be to think of sets and
functions right so every box will be a
function of its input wires into its
output wires. So you think of cartisian
product or you get a multiple inputs and
you get multiple outputs. Um I guess
sets in and relations are super
interesting too. Uh instead of um so I I
guess in that case you can you can do a
lot fancier diagrams. Um if you think of
relation so you don't have inputs and
outputs anymore but you can essentially
think of them going both ways. Um then I
guess yeah um the main example of these
monoidal categories uh was to do linear
algebra to sort of formalize u things
that physicists were already doing uh
drawing diagrams linear maps as
diagrams. So I guess that's the main
example. Um and in our case what we're
interested in uh will be more something
like the category of measurable spaces
and stoastic maps. So we'll think of
each wire as a measurable space with the
product space being the tensor the the
operation that puts wires side by side
and then um a box will be um essentially
a stoastic map that takes a product
space and gives you a new product space.
Um and so I guess with this
interpretation in mind um essentially a
graphical model a pro generative model
is precisely a diagram with an
interpretation in stock. So I guess yeah
um the then the main way to formulate
this idea is essentially to define
what's called a funtor um is going to be
a morphism of categories. So something
that translates a signature into another
and also preserves identity composition
and tensor. Um and then you have this
sort of main theorem that tells you that
diagrams are the free monoidal category.
So what this means uh intuitively is
that if you want to define a funtor from
the category of diagrams, the only thing
you need to do is to define an
interpretation for each wire and an
interpretation for each box. So on the
left hand side you've got all the
funtors from C sigma to D. And here
you've got all these sort of much
smaller objects where um essentially you
just need uh measurable space for each
of the wires and uh a stochastic map for
each of the boxes um and or conditional
probability um and now you get an
interpretation for each composition of
these. Um, so that's sort of the the
structural theorem, the sort of
foundational theorem that justifies why
are string diagrams the right data
structure when you're um looking at
composition in sequence and in parallel.
Um, any composition, any such
composition is a diagram.
Um and so I guess with that theorem in
mind like on the right hand side you've
got something that you can represent as
a small data structure that uh that that
is uh you just need uh the
representation for a stoastic map for
each of the boxes in your diagram. And
on the left hand side you've got the
sort of algorithm that's going to take
these diagrams and compute their their
meaning by plugging these um
distributions together and essentially
performing inference. So on on the right
hand side you've got you've got
something um that is sort of data like
on the left hand side you you've got the
algorithm that's gonna compute that data
to give you um inference algorithms.
Um and I guess yeah I was um promising
some some short um detour into uh
quantum uh natural language processing.
So I guess here it's just a small code
snippet to um show I guess how concise
you can make um a particular model if
you write it as a functor. Um so here uh
we've got boxes are worlds. So we've got
a a box for Alice, a box for love, and a
box for Bob. We're going to compose them
together uh according to their
grammatical structure. So here the the
the word Alice is connected to love via
this cup and the word bub is connected
to love via that cup. And overall you
get a sentence. Um so that's the sort of
natural language side of things. And
then you get the quantum side of things
by saying look every noun I'm just going
to interpret it as a cubit. So as a
quantum system that I can control um the
noun alice is going to be one state of
the cubit the state zero. The word bub
is going to be the state one. And now
the world love is going to be where
interesting stuff happens where I'm
going to entangle or correlate my inputs
and my outputs my subject and my object.
And so here you represent it as a
quantum circuit that's going to be some
some hard gate and some control gate. So
essentially a bunch of quantum gates
represented as boxes that you compose in
sequence and in parallel. So I won't get
into much quantum theory here, but I
guess the the main punch line is that
you can replace quantum by um
probabilistic um circuits and the same
theory applies in a sense that um you
get this compositional way of
interpreting well natural language but
interpreting any sort of compositional
system in general. So here you take your
sentence. You apply the funtor to it.
You will get uh a circuit a quantum
circuit and then essentially this eval
is going to be a second step of the
funtor that's going to take your quantum
circuit and turn it into um a bunch of
matrices. So it's going to turn it into
vector spaces and linear maps and
compute the meaning of that circuit,
compute the meaning of that sentence.
Right? So I guess that's one QNLP
experiment in um in a few lines of
Python. And I guess yeah the argument
for this talk would be that we can
replace quantum with uh with active
inference here and and get a very
similar recipe for how to build uh
larger um active inference systems from
smaller ones in their interaction.
Um so yeah I guess that was my thesis
three years of PhD thesis in one slide.
Uh so let's uh let's move on. Um the
yeah I guess I'll try and give some of
the sort of necessary theory to um to
look at active inference formally uh but
give it all in terms of diagrams rather
than complicated formula. So now that
you've seen a bunch of diagrams, uh you
can you you've noticed that you if you
only have tensor in parallel and in
sequence, you can you can only do planer
diagrams. If you want um if you want
arbitrary diagrams, you need this
special swap. Um and the swap is going
to just satisfy these four aums you see
here. If you swap with nothing, it
doesn't do anything. If you swap and
swap back, it doesn't do anything. If
you swap F and G, it's the same as doing
G and F and then swap. And finally, you
can decompose a complex swap in terms of
basic swaps. So that's all you need to
get a symmetric monoidal category. Um,
and essentially in in a symmetric
category, you don't care about the order
of wires because you can permute them.
So in the case of probability theory,
you don't care about the order of your
probabilistic model. you can permute the
variables. Um what matters is what's
connected to what via boxes not the
order of the inputs and the outputs. Um
and um yeah I guess in natural language
you do care about the order of words. So
in that case you're not symmetric. Um
but um another kind of category once you
have symmetric is um is the idea of a
compact category and that's where you
have the ability of bending wires. So I
guess in a normal string diagram the
wires are going to flow from the inputs
to the outputs. Um in a compact diagram
you can flow backward and
um in the first paper applying category
theory to be basian inference that was
the technical apparatus to formalize the
idea of um Beijian inversing. So I guess
with these cups and caps you can take um
a joint distribution on a * b and bend
one of the legs to get a stochastic map
from a to b. And similarly if you have
um if you have a stoastic map you can
bend the output and get u a joint
distribution. And now uh if you have a
stoastic map from A to B and you have a
prior on A um so I guess that's the the
little trick that they had to hide is
this little box uh this little black box
on on the cup here. Uh then you can
invert um you can perform Beijian
inversion and you will get um a stoastic
map from B to A. Um and I guess um yeah
what there are many ways of formalizing
this uh caveat of you need a prior if
you want to be able to do uh Beijian
inversion um and yeah I guess I won't
get too much into the the literature of
how you you formalize uh categories of
uh stoastic processes are a very big
topic but in that context having a
compact category means essentially every
object every uh wire comes with a prior
um and now when you invert you use that
prior
um so yeah I guess in quantum it's got a
very different interpretation where
these wires are going to represent bell
states entangled states and entangled
measurements and then this equation
amounts to teleportation in the context
of basian probability uh this equation
is just the basian inversion of uh a
trivial
probabilistic channel um is itself. So I
guess not very interesting in quantum
it's like wow we can teleport things in
in Beijan. Uh it's just the inverse of
the identity is the identity. Um so
that's yeah that's a compact category.
Um you can bend things around. So if you
have symmetric plus compact you can
truly talk about a graph structure for
your diagrams because you can connect
any input to any output uh in a
graph-like way.
Um so now I guess an important
ingredient um we've seen for um defining
a generative model is the ability to use
the same variable in multiple places. Um
so that's formalized in terms of these
common monoids. So you have an operation
that splits a wire and it's um
co-commutative. So if you split and then
you swap it's the same thing as just uh
splitting. Um it's got a unit which is
discarding. So if you split and then if
you if you copy something and then you
discard or if you split and then you
terminate a wire you haven't done
anything and it's coassociative. So it
doesn't matter if if you copy the left
hand copy or the right hand copy you get
three identical copies. Um and yeah I
guess the main two axioms for being a
cartisian category are these two. So the
the second one I guess um you can call
normalization. So essentially in terms
of stoastic maps what this means is that
if you um apply a stoastic map and then
take the weight of the result or take
the mass of the result um for any
distribution coming in here it's the
same as the mass of the result uh as the
mass of the input. So essentially if you
have a normal it takes a normalized um
it takes a normalized uh distribution to
a normalized distribution. Um and so on
the left hand side is more controversial
is not going to be true in the category
of stoastic maps. Uh this says that f is
deterministic. So if you perform f and
then copy the result is the same as
copying the inputs and performing f
twice. And I I guess if you take the
special case where f has no input, this
means that essentially um f can be
copied means that um it's deterministic
in a sense that performing f if f was a
toss coin, right? Um you would take f
throw throw a coin and then copy the
result um you would get a different
result as if you cop you you you toss
two coins, right? So um the second one
um is going to hold in terms of Beijian
probability theory if you have
normalized processes and it's this idea
of essentially you can also formalize it
as causality. So if you discard the
output it cannot influence the input.
Um and um yeah the first one is
essentially what brings you back to the
world of deterministic processes. So
it's a good way of characterizing which
stoastic map is in fact a deterministic
one. And so if you have um if you have
these two axioms you're called a
cartisian category. If you don't have
them you're called a copy discard
category. And so I guess um in our
context we're really interested in copy
discard categories where these two are
different processes. Um and yeah, I
guess what what can you prove at this
abstract level of of generality
um is a a really nice no cloning theorem
where you don't need to assume any
complex numbers or any quantum stuff and
in fact it holds as well in the context
of probability theory. Um and it's I I
think it's called the no broadcasting
theorem in that in that case. Um but the
the idea is that you cannot have both
cups and capsu uh and copying. So here I
guess you assume that you have cups and
then because you have copying then the
the copy of a cup is also going to is
going to be two cups right. Um but you
can also uh you can also do some
shenanigans where you you bend the wires
because copying is co-commutative. So on
one side you're going to you're going to
you're going to bend the wire. You're
going to swap the wires. And now you've
essentially proved that two cups like
this side by side are actually equal to
two cups nested inside out. Um you bend
all the legs and you get that a swap is
equal to the identity which is basically
um yeah um it means you've done
something wrong, right? like if you
can't even distinguish swapping stuff
from not doing anything, your category
is uh very much trivial. So I guess
that's the main the no cloning theorem
is that if you're both compact, so you
have cups and caps and copying now uh
you have to be a trivial category in the
sense that everything is a essentially a
scalar multiple of the identity. Um so
um that's not the case in probability
theory. So probability theory also has
this no cloning feature and that's
essentially well you can't copy uh you
you can't copy something if it's a
non-trivial distribution you can't copy
uh a correlated u state right um the
same way you can't copy an entangled
state in in quantum um so yeah um I
guess um the last ingredient we need in
order to talk about active inference is
the idea they have normalization um and
it in the context of string diagrams
that's going to be represented as I was
saying by hierarchical diagrams where
you have a sub diagram that's uh
inducted lines will just represent the
normalization of it with some caveat if
there's no support for the um for the
particular state. So um here you have um
a stoastic map from X to Y and you put
it inside of a dotted line and you get
its um its normalization. So I guess the
guy inside is not really a stoastic map
anymore. It's more of a just any
measurable function. Um not necessarily
normalized and the thing outside becomes
a proper stoastic map. Um and that means
for any um measurable function you can
decompose it in terms of uh something
that's uh normalized and then something
that you discount. So these three lines
are the the discounting operation uh
that we drew as a as a white dot before.
But um so essentially here that equation
tells you that every measurable function
is going to be a normalized one up to
some renormalization. So I guess it's
sort of intuitive and also normalization
behaves nicely with respect to parallel
composition. So if you have f and gum
and then par you normalize them you get
the normalization of f thanks to the
normalization of g it behaves well with
respect to copying uh a particular um
variable of your generative model. Um
but the thing it doesn't behave well
with is the composition. So it's uh not
true that the normalization of
composition is the composition of
normalization and that's um essentially
what gives you the difference between a
Jeffrey update and a pearl update in the
in the context of of Beijian inference.
Um so on the left hand side you've got a
Jeffrey update where you first normalize
and then pre-ompose with the prior.
on the right hand side you've got your
pearl update where you do um first the
pre-omposition with the prior and then
you normalize and so I guess um here on
the left if you want to obtain something
normalized over row you will need to
renormalize so like you get two
normalizations on the right hand side
you only get one and that's sort of the
difference that's the the fact that
normalization is not a funtor in a sense
it doesn't commute with the composition
Um so um then another kind of bubble
we'll need is uh taking the logarithm of
a function. Um so if we have a function
from x to the reals positive reals um we
can take its logarithm this function is
just going to be uh if we if we think of
the category of measurable functions
well it's um it's um the empty diagram
is going to correspond to the real
numbers to the one-dimensional space and
so um such a function will just be a box
an effect which takes uh something and
gives you just reormalization factor,
right? Um and now if you have such an
effect, you can put it into a green box
and you'll get the uh the negative log
of it. Um so that's sort of a mere um
sort of notational gadget. Um and
essentially yeah it only becomes
interesting if you start using it um
inside a more complex diagram where this
um this green box will not in will not
commute past the composition and will
give some interesting hierarchical
structure to your to your diagram. And I
guess here I'm just copying some caveats
from um from the the to um to Ital
paper. Um, and yeah, I guess they they
give some some pointers to some
interesting category theory that could
be formalized to um to to explore these
log boxes further. But um in our context
where we need them to is essentially
yeah we just want the the nice
properties of logarithms. So if uh this
copying operator acts like um
essentially a product uh then we want
that the log of a product is the sum of
the logs. So you get this sort of nice
um nice operation um nice um yeah
homorphism property of the log um the
discarding operator it acts like the
unit of this um multiplication. So the
log of the units will be uh zero. Um and
then you get this nice product rule um
this sort of lightnit rule for the
logarithm of of a tensor product in that
sense will be the sum of two tensor
products. So that's also the kind of
equation you'll find in a sort of
automatic differentiation uh framework
where the gradient of d tensor e is
going to be the gradient of d plus the
gradient of e. Um and finally if x is
deterministic so that's what they call
sharp states. Um then you it also
commutes past the the log. Um so you get
these nice property of the the logarithm
which allows to take a diagram with
these green boxes and sort of massage
them into uh a sum of diagrams. Um and
finally you can define uh this notion of
open vibrational free energy where
instead of looking at the free energy of
a closed model uh so something that
wouldn't have an input I here um so just
a joint distribution over states uh
internal states and observed variables
you have this idea of an open uh model
so you have some of the inputs that you
can control um and Now you can define
the free energy of this model with
respect to joint distribution on uh the
inputs with respect to the and the
internal state and uh a prior on the
observed variables and uh here's the
formula. So I guess that was sort of the
the main uh point of the paper was to
build all these categorical apparatus to
get to the point where you can just um
draw the definition of free energy as
diagram. Um and then the main theorem uh
being that essentially uh this gives you
a compositional
um definition in a sense that the free
energy for uh composition. So here it's
the tensor composition. Um the free
energy of the tensor will be some
composition of the individual thing. So
I guess in the case of tensor is the
simplest case. uh I won't show the the
case for sequential composition where
you need to to take um a more uh
complicated uh operation to compose the
the subsystems. But I guess that's sort
of the the main theorem of that um
categorical active inference framework
is that you get um this idea that the
free energy for the whole is composition
of the free energy of its parts and
essentially yeah mono category theory
gives you the sort of um the high level
uh layer of abstraction to describe
these sorts of compositional phenomenon.
Um and yeah I guess with this uh sort of
foundational theory
um you want to turn into application and
so I guess that's what this copay was uh
built for. So what we already have um to
support this sort of of active inference
implementation in terms of diagrams well
we we have most of the finite
dimensional case uh implemented already
in the sense that if your u if your
random variable span a categorical
distribution is a categorical
distribution then you can turn this
basian inference problem into a tensor
network contraction problem. Um we have
a bunch of automatic and diagrammatic
differentiation uh algorithms
implemented uh with some um compilation
uh with the JAX library. So essentially
you can take your diagram and compile it
into a bunch of GPU code for very fast
execution. Um and finally um the sort of
more experimental more speculative um
part of the library is this idea of the
the geometry of interaction where you
formalize birectional processes. So
sadly I won't have much time to to get
into um that side of things but there's
this very interesting idea of a basian
lens where you have um these birectional
operations that also have some
stochastic side to them. So essentially
you can talk about uh updates about the
the forward part of your process being
some inference and the backward part
being some update and this geometry of
interaction will give you a way of
composing these updates together um in a
compositional structure of vision
inference. So um we already have the
sort of purely uh abstract
implementation of this geometry of
interaction. What's missing is sort of
plugging these two things together. So
just looking at how if you take finite
dimensional as a first step uh and you
look at how it updates um you should be
able to implement it in a purely
compositional way uh with disco and also
be able to draw the result in the end um
and I guess what's missing would be um a
more um continuous um um implementation
where um I guess to go beyond finite
dimensional uh you need some sort of um
yeah more involved implementation based
on monads I guess is a very
well-developed um theory on the category
side um and there's one thing we've
started working on which is this idea of
delayed interaction where um essentially
you can represent discrete time
processes so you have a very natural way
of talking about time series time um and
yeah I guess what the the the main
ingredient that's missing to develop
this this further would be having
experimentalists are ready to to take
the challenge to build their experiments
in a way that you can compose them with
other experiments in the future and
build it upon uh a theory of how to
compose processes together. So I guess
um that was sort of the main uh
objective of disco was to sort of lower
the entry to uh the cost of entry to
understanding string diagram so that any
experimentalist from quantum computing
or active inference can pick up just
enough uh abstract mathematics to turn
um turn these experiments into something
you can compose together. Um, and yeah,
I guess um I'd be happy to to get some
some questions from the audience and
looking forward to um to more
interactions with the the active
inference community. Um, thanks for the
thanks a lot.
Thank you. Great talk. Okay, anyone
watching live can write a question in
the live chat and I wrote down some
questions as well. First though, just to
kind of pull back like how did you get
into writing Disco Pi? what brought you
to wanting to build this toolkit and
what made you interested in the area?
Yeah, I mean so I guess it started with
the the master's thesis in Oxford was um
mostly quantum stuff uh with the course
that Bob Kirk was teaching there and um
I was interested in AI already and NLP
in particular at the time and I guess um
yeah there was this program of bridging
the two together and making quantum NLP
uh and so I I got involved in that and
when it came to implementing it, it felt
like it would be a shame to implement uh
quantum NLP uh as a as a oneshot thing
where you build your experiment and
throw it away. And I guess um we took it
as an excuse to develop something that
we thought was much more broadly
applicable where you take this um
general theory of monoto categories and
implement that and use Q&L as a sort of
proof of concept that it can do
something useful and then hope that
other people will start formalizing more
stuff as monoid categories. So I guess
this uh paper from to Ital came much
after the the thesis and um I guess um
they took active inference as as um
something that you could formalize with
diagrams too. So yeah um I I guess QNLP
was a bit of an excuse to get into some
very cool maths and to develop some some
cool software to back it up. And now I'm
sort of yeah looking forward to to
seeing other ways to to apply this
software. Awesome. Okay. I'm going to
read and answer one question from the
live chat and then I'll ask you a
question. So Dival wrote is this under a
specific group project at active
inference institute like ontology or
other project. So just to briefly
address that it could be super relevant
for ontology. We could use the active
inference ontology to extract natural
language descriptions of generative
models for example represent them in
disco. So it could be a tool used in
ontology project or it could be spun up
as a category theory project as we've
done in the past when we for example
focused on some of Toby uh Sinclair
Smith's work. So everyone's welcome to
uh get get involved and reactivate
projects as they are excited by. This is
definitely something exciting. So, so
let me ask you this question. How do we
connect the properties of diagrams for
example the ability to swap capture
causality and the error of time cups and
caps and all that with the features of
cognitive systems which we're interested
in? Like how do we know which kinds of
formal constraints are overkill,
nonsequittor?
How do we really like reconcile
and build with the right formal systems
when we're dealing with embodied
cognitive systems that don't on a first
pass have those kinds of constraints?
Yeah. Um I think that's a super
interesting question and in a sense like
not being an expert in active inference
I don't feel entitled to to really say
what are the properties that you guys
are interested in but I guess as a sort
of parallel to other ways diagrams have
been applied in in particularly in
quantum I felt like one interesting way
to look at at diagrams is to to look at
them in terms of comtorial structures
that have some um some structural
properties that you can exploit to turn
the turn the computational problems
associated with them into tractable
problems. So I guess the maybe as a as a
bet I would say that characterizing
which models are efficiently simulable
simulatable or not is sort of a key
question that you ask yourself when you
you you get to build a model of of um
cognition in general in a sense that if
you cannot simulate it, if you cannot um
um build an efficient implementation for
it, then it's likely that the brain
isn't going be working that way in a
sense the brain is efficiently solving
uh this cognition problem. So behind it
there must be some sort of um tractable
algorithm and I guess there's a way of
characterizing which um problems will be
tractable by the shape of the diagrams
associated with them. So one particular
um way this this happens is uh when you
look at tensor networks um uh if you can
bound the the width of your diagram and
make it look like it's uh almost a tree
and you have this idea of bounded tree
width where um you can show that your uh
your network has some sort of
hierarchical structure to it where it's
shaped in terms of a main route that
splits into branches. Even if these
branches are thick in a sense, it's not
necessarily a tree, then this bounded uh
tree width will give you a bound on how
hard it will be to compute this tensor
network. So in a sense um from the the
sort of graph structure of your diagram
uh from the fact that this graph has a
nice decomposition you can u exploit
that fact and turn it into an efficient
algorithm um to solve uh inference on
that model to um contract the tensor
network in the case of physicists. But
um I think this general principle uh
applies in a very broad range of cases.
Um and there's some like very deep um
intersections with complexity theory
where um I guess this P and NP question
is all about like how do you separate
between things that you can solve
efficiently or not, right? Um so uh
diagrams give you an interesting way of
looking at this P versus NP question
where the yeah I guess you can try and
tell apart these two classes by looking
at the shape of diagrams that represent
these
problems.
Awesome. Okay. So, what makes the
variational free energy open or not
open? And then some more VF related
questions. How how did you connect that
to the log properties since of course
the free energy is used as a bound on
log probabilities as surprise. And then
what does it mean that the VFE is
compositional since from a numerical
perspective the compositionality is kind
of trivial? Like of course I could
calculate the free energy for two
different situations and just add those
numbers together. So what do we really
get with the semantics of composition
that go beyond just calculating two
numbers and then adding those two
numbers?
Yeah. So um I guess to go back to to
that definition of uh open free energy
um I guess the yeah the main difference
here compared to the the standard
definition is this extra wire I right so
you I guess
um the the idea is that if this wire uh
is empty uh if there's no particular
input you get back to the usual
definition um and it um It's the idea of
instead of trying to compute the free
energy of a big monolithic system that
represent your the overall thing you
want to study. Um you first decompose
that into a composition of uh different
things being independent and being
composed in sequence. So that's where
you get the the correlation and this
decomposition of your problem will give
you a formula to compute the the the
composition of the the corresponding
free energies. And I guess um this
example wasn't necessarily the the best
one to pick. So here it's the the fact
that it's compositional with respect to
independent uh uh parallel composition.
Uh where I guess yeah it's a bit of a
trivial property of free energy that um
the free energy of the tensor of two
things will be the sum of their free
energies. Um and I guess um I yeah um I
should have included the more
interesting case where you have a
sequential composition of things and
where this um sequential composition
gives you a non-trivial way of
decomposing the formula for your free
energy. So I guess that would be the the
place where you can get some some
traction in a particular experiment
where essentially um you can yeah I
guess the same way that an automatic
differentiation uh framework would um
would use the structure of your program
to compute the structure of its
derivative. Well, here you could have um
yeah, I guess automatic free energy idea
of the structure of your um the
structure of your model informs the
structure of the formula for its free
energy and potentially implying some um
some algorithmic speed up. So I guess
here obviously there isn't any speed up
to be found in this particular um in
this particular
um instance of compositionality and um
yeah I guess I I'm yeah I don't feel
qualified enough to uh advance any
conjecture on how the the non-trivial
case would uh give you algorithmic
speedups but I guess that's the the sort
of of promise and there's there's the
idea of a speed up there's also the idea
of having software ware that's more
modular. So having software that um for
one experiment that you can potentially
reuse to compose with a later
experiment. Um yeah, like where where
that kind of lands for me is we can use
these nested box structures to reflect
the articulations of
different causal and spatial and
temporal systems in sequence and in
parallel and also proposed cognitive
mechanisms. So not necessarily related
to the material connections on substrate
but related to different kinds of
interactions amongst like attention,
memory, all these kinds of cognitive
features. So, first there's the benefit
of the interpretability, legibility,
modularity, reuse, angle, and then
getting to that speed up. If it's
possible to have strong decomposition
composition type rules, large boxes with
a lot of stuff in them, whether that's
100 nestmates in a multi- aent
simulation or 100 different cognitive
systems in a complex single agent
simulation, those can
be brought down to their most atomic
computational rules and possibly certain
kinds of calculations.
will have certain methods that would be
like the most effective for this kind of
distribution or for this size.
So that gives a unified way to look at
the topology of information flows and
calculations in a notational disco pi
framework rather than those connections
being kind of
semi-implicit in the control flow of a
Python script or maybe scattered across
different files with different functions
calling each other, not necessarily in a
unified way. For example, a common
approach is like to have an agent class
and then have them be communicating back
and forth with an environment. And that
could still be really well structured,
but it leads to kind of a fundamental
division between what's happening within
the agent and within the environment.
And
that's understandable and a useful
design pattern. However, the stronger
direction to kind of steer towards would
be
unifying systems for notation possibly
like disco pi that could get us like the
best of both worlds with well
ststructured interfaces and unification
across really different representations.
Yeah, I think one also one important
aspect um is is this idea of separation
of concern between syntax and semantics
where uh you want the ability to
describe your models in a syntactic way
that will be reused in different cases
with different semantics in mind,
different ways of computing inference on
the same diagram, right? And so with
this idea of uh separating you have the
diagrams on one side that represent the
um description of your model itself and
then you have the funtors that describe
what the computation you do on that
model. And I think this separation of
concern means that well you can compose
the syntax together and compose these
descriptions to form a larger
description. Um and then that way of
building your model will inform the
computation side of things. And um I
guess yeah speedups are sort of the one
of the theoretical results you could or
experimental results you could get out
of this. And I guess I mean other ways
of thinking about it. I think when
you're talking about topology, it really
um it really feels like there there's
some connection to be made there in a
sense that a lot of what people do with
these diagrams is try and embed them
onto some topological space where your
computation doesn't live in the abstract
anymore and is actually embedded in a
particular space. And I guess for
physicists this will be like embedded
into spaceime you know so you will have
like these relativistic quantum uh
mechanics ideas where you have quantum
processes on a on a manifold for your
space time. But I think that a similar
idea uh can can be used to take your
abstract description of a generative
model and embed it onto an actual um
topological space which is the sort of
space-like um organization of a
particular brain or a particular
machine. Right. Um
cool. Yeah. I I think of the saying uh
slow is smooth and smooth is fast. Like
the speed up sounds like it's going to
be the pot of gold at the end of the
rainbow, but actually the modularity and
the legibility of the software is what
is going to get that infrastructure
grade long-term templated reuse of
cognitive models. And if those take
slightly longer to run than some super
special case optimized situation, first
off, we're only going to get to that
optimized runtime from the modular
design. And then in in the end I think
it's going to be the
compositionality that leads to
ecosystems of components that are
effective and then speed can be sort of
a secondary consideration that's runtime
and situation specific. But like the
benefits of
bringing category theory to active
inference, I hope we can draw out over
the coming months and years because it
really represents a upgrade in how these
models are are represented and
communicated and they kind of bring an
aesthetic
possibility with its own grammar that is
clearly to be learned.
and also a really strong machine
readability. So I hope that people who
view this are excited to try Disco Py
and that we can continue to like look
back at the models that have been built
and bring them into these notation
systems to demonstrate how they can
exactly recapitulate and give
reproducibility to past examples. And I
think that act alone is going to reveal
a sort of adjacent
possible and it would be awesome if that
could all be happening in a flexible
environment like Disco Pi. Yeah, I I
can't agree more. I mean, I think
there's a similar effort that's been
going on on the machine learning side
where people have taken category theory
to formulize existing models and it's
always the question of okay, I mean, you
can do existing stuff, but what's the um
what's the new stuff you can do with it?
And I I feel like yeah, active inference
is definitely a place where you can look
for this these new models where
potentially there's um there's something
there that you can um describe in a
succinct elegant way using categories
and show has some experimental value in
practice and I guess software is going
to be key to turn these theoretical
insights into experimental um
experimental value and and I think yeah
um this
This ability of category theory to make
bridges between different topics and to
to make metaphors become formal is also
a good way to uh get inspiration uh from
other fields into active inference and
and back. So I think um I guess yeah it
would be super exciting that the same
library gets used by quantum natural
language processing people and active
inference that have a priority nothing
to do with each other. Um,
cool. Well, do you have any last
comments? And also like what directions
are you taking it now with the package
or just in your own work?
Um, yeah. Yeah, I mean I guess
um we're looking very much for
contributors especially um people who
can bring um projects to apply uh the
library in new directions and so um
please get in touch on on GitHub or
otherwise uh and we'll be yeah very
happy to um to welcome new people to the
the disco pipe uh contributors and uh in
terms of new directions we're pushing it
in uh I guess uh yeah the sort of
education effort is something we're um
trying to invest a lot of time in. So we
uh spend a lot of time writing
documentation, examples, notebooks. Uh
hopefully uh we'll lower the barrier to
entry to something that's quite scary at
first. The I mean category theory is one
of the most intimidating topics out
there. So making it more childish and
talk about snakes and spiders and sort
of making it fun uh is the part of it.
uh and uh I guess yeah in terms of
development I think um there's a lot of
work on category theory for
probabilities um and I think um that has
a very strong connection with functional
programming like I guess there's this
monet um library in high school that uh
implements um a lot of um Beijian
inference in terms of monads and uh very
elegantly in terms of category theory. I
think some of that could be ported to to
Python um and built into disco pi so
that you could um potentially yeah um go
beyond sort of toy examples where you
have a bunch of categorical
distributions and go into something
where it's um yeah a very um powerful
system that can handle all kinds of uh
Beijian inference problems and in the
same um same sort of nice looking
diagram
The future is diagrammed.
Yeah, that's I mean matrices were the
maths of the 20th century. Um diagrams
will be u the maths of the 21st.
Cool. Thank you very much. Looking
forward to learning more and appreciate
all the work and the outreach that you
all do. So yeah, thanks a lot for the
invite and hope uh get in touch very
soon. Thank you. Bye. Take care.